hey what's up guys my name is a turn-on
welcome back to my stable spas series so
today we will be talking all about
sorting in C++ so talking about various
different data structures and as the
series goes on we will continue talking
about various data structures because
data structures are how you store data
and data is very important when you're
programming and dealing with signals bus
what we haven't talked about yet is how
do you sort the data that you have so
suppose that I have a vector or an array
of values integers and I want them to be
sorted by their value or by some kind of
predicate how do I actually gets
impossible to sort something for me now
obviously you could just write your own
algorithm like bubble sort a quick sort
or any kind of algorithm that just
iterates through the list and source the
elements into the order that you want
them to be sorted in that's totally fine
and there are cases when you would want
to do something like that
however usually if you're dealing with
simple sports kind of with its inbuilt
collection types like STD vector there's
no reason for you to have to write an
algorithm yourself if you could just get
the disabled spot library to do the
sorting for you and that's why today
we're going to focus on something called
STD sort which is a sort function that's
kind of built into this tablecloth
library that can actually perform that
sorting for you over any kind of
iterator that you provide it with so if
we pop over to CBP reference so come and
take a look at STDs so it you can see we
have this function here that will sort
elements in a certain range that we
provide it with and what we have to
provide it with is essentially just an
iterator and beginning interrater and an
end iterate and everything inside that
iterator will be sorted based on a
certain predicate that we provide it
with so what we can do is kind of just
not provide it with any kind of
predicate and we'll just attempt to sort
of kind of in order based on the type or
we can actually give it some kind of
function for it to actually use for
comparison and we can provide it with a
lambda as well which we'll take a look
at it doesn't have any kind of return
value and the complexity for sorting is
n times log n which is fairly good so if
we jump back here into our source code
let's take a look at a basic example so
what I'll do here is I'll create a
vector it could be an array doesn't
really matter of integers I'll call
these values and I'll just provide some
basic values let's just say three five
one four two okay so these are clearly
not in order
promoting any kind of water they're in a
bit of a random order here I'll include
vector and also include algorithms that
we get STDs sort and what I want to do
with this vector now is I want to sort
this in ascending order so they go from
one two three four five so to do that
what I'll do is I'll just type in STDs
sort I'll pass in the start of this
vector iterator which is values don't
begin the end wishes values or end so
that provides it with a range and they
don't I need to provide some kind of
predicate now if I don't provide any
kind of predicate so best I don't
provide it with a function for it to
perform this sorting it will just sort
it in ascending order in the case of
integers here so in other words if I was
a princess to the console after the
sorting happens I'll say for unit value
inside values let's do a CBC out the
value just like that at five then you'll
see I get a perfectly sorted list if I
do want to provide some kind of a way
for it to sort I can do that by passing
in a function and this can be either
literally a function inside like a
stroke that you do you make or it can be
a lambda so there are quite a few
built-in ones as well if I go to include
functional I can use something like STD
Breda
for example with ant just like that
if I can hit that five this will sort it
based on the greater value so you can
see that I get five four three two one
and finally I'll write a lambda as well
so I'll get rid of this and I'll just
have a normal lambda in a into B and
then I'll explain this a bit so it's
either C I'm basically just providing it
with a function that it's going to use
to sort these values now based on the
documentation you can see that this this
comparison function returns a bool so
true or false and it returns true if the
first argument so that is the first
argument that we pass in here into the
parameter is less than so is ordered
before the second so basically what that
means is that if we give it two values a
and B which one of these should appear
first in the list that's kind of what
we're trying to determine here and if we
return true it means that a will be
ordered before B whereas if we return
false then they will be before a so as a
basic example let's just let it sort
this you know in a
in order from one to five so what I'll
do here is I'll simply say return a less
than B so if a is less than B we'll sort
it to the front of the list
let's hit at five and you can see that I
get the same result as we had before and
if I reverse this and obviously it's
going to sort it the other way around
where if a is greater than B it's going
to fall to the front which means that
the bigger values get sorted to the
front and then let's just do something
for fun let's just make it so that one
goes to the very end I think this
demonstrates the predicate pretty well
as well so if we say if a is one what do
we want to do well if a is currently the
first value we want to move to the back
of the list so in other words we want to
return false because we don't want it to
be ordered before B however if B is one
then we want a to actually move to the
final list and the way that we do that
is we return true
because if we return true it means that
move a to the front of the list right so
if I change this back to what it was so
that we still have a before B and I hit
f5 you can see that we get our list in
ascending order except for one which is
at the end so anyway that was a pretty
basic and quick example of how to use
SUV sort and sorting a simple plus in
general sorting is of course very useful
you can do this with all types doesn't
have to be integers integers that are
just really easy to show because they're
literally numbers and we kind of I used
to sing them in a particular order you
can do this with strings you can do this
with this with custom classes that's
what this predicate here this lambda
that we could supply is so useful
because that means that we can set the
rules and it doesn't rely on only
working on inbuilt types or anything
like that we can use this with anything
finally we have a bit of a quick video
if you're trying to do these for ages
and we end up just making in 58 20
minutes long but anyway sorting really
useful let me know what you can give
this if you have another way or other
kind of scenarios in which this stuff is
useful and some predators that might
work really well then just leave a
comment below and we can kind of talk
about it I hope you guys enjoyed the
video if you did you can hit the like
button you can also have support series
by going to patreon I'll come for such
the cherokees thank you as always to all
the lovely people who helped support
this series and make it possible I will
see you guys in the next video goodbye
[Music]